Guide to the Stephen Parks Research Collection on John Dutton
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Stephen Parks research collection on John Dunton
1962-1972
OSB MSS 103
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.77
(4 boxes)
Correspondence, research copies, and writings documenting Stephen Parks's research on John Dunton and the English book trade. Correspondents include Dunton scholars Robert Haig, S. Hodgson, Patricia Köster, and Gilbert McEwen, as well as the American Antiquarian Society, British Museum, Glasgow University Library, and the Union Theological Seminary Library. Research copies consist of photocopies and photostats of primary and secondary sources. Copies of primary sources include two volumes of Dunton manuscripts from the Bodleian Library, Ms Rawlinson D.71 and D.72; Dunton's will and that of his father, Rev. John Dunton; Dunton imprints; and legal papers. Copies of secondary sources include a Harvard University Ph.D. dissertation, "The True Secret History of Mr. John Dunton," by Theodore Merryman Hatfield, 1926. Also includes reprints of two papers by Parks, "John Dunton and The Works of the Learned," and "Bookseller's Trade Sales," both from the journal The Library, 1968 and 1969.
Parks, Stephen, 1940-
Dunton, John, 1659-1733
Hatfield, Theodore Merryman
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Stephen Parks, February 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
John Dunton (1659-1732) was a London bookseller during the late seventeenth and early eighteenth centuries. He was the son of Rev. John Dunton (1628-1676). After an apprenticeship from 1674 to 1681, Dunton went into business, primarily dealing in devotional works, sermons, political works, and chapbooks, as well as periodicals. The Athenian Gazette (1691-1697) was Dunton's most successful publication, and it influenced many eighteenth century periodicals. Another notable work was his Life and Errors of John Dunton, Citizen of London (1705), an early example of English autobiography. In his later years Dunton's bookselling business declined with his poor health, and he resorted to pamphleteering to support himself. He died in London on November 24, 1732.
Stephen Parks was the Curator of the James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Collection at the Beinecke Rare Book & Manuscript Library from 1972 to 2004. Parks's study of John Dunton, John Dunton and the English Book Trade: A Study of His Career with a Checklist of his Publications was published by Garland Publishing, Inc. in 1976.
Scope and Contents
The Stephen Parks Research Collection on John Dunton consists of correspondence and research materials, spanning the years 1962-1972. The collection documents Stephen Parks's research regarding John Dunton (1659-1732), a London bookseller. The collection is housed in 4 boxes (including 3 oversize boxes), and has been organized into three series: Research Correspondence, Research Copies, and Writings of Stephen Parks.
Series I, Research Correspondence, is arranged alphabetically by correspondent in folders 1-11. The correspondence includes incoming letters and copies of outgoing correspondence. Correspondents include John Dunton scholars Robert Haig, S. Hodgson, Patricia Köster, and Gilbert McEwen, as well as the following repositories: the American Antiquarian Society, the British Museum, Glasgow University Library, and Union Theological Seminary.
Series II, Research Copies, consists of bound and loose photocopies and photostats, and is arranged into two subseries, Primary Sources and Secondary Sources, in folders 12-21, and 24-29 (oversize). Primary Sources include two volumes of Dunton manuscripts from the Bodleian Library, Ms Rawlinson D.71 and D.72; John Dunton's will and that of his father, Rev. John Dunton; John Dunton imprints; and legal papers. Secondary Sources include a Harvard University Ph.D. dissertation, "The True Secret History of Mr. John Dunton," by Theordore Merryman Hatfield, 1926, and a few dealer catalogs.
Series III, Writings of Stephen Parks, is arranged chronologically in folders 22-23. It consists of two reprints of papers by Stephen Parks, "John Dunton and The Works of The Learned ," and "Bookseller's Trade Sales," both published in The Library (Oxford University Press, 1968, 1969).
Book industries and trade -- England -- History; Booksellers and bookselling -- England -- London; Dunton, John, 1627 or 1628-1676; Dunton, John, 1659-1733 -- Manuscripts; Parks, Stephen, 1940-
- Research Correspondence, 1962-1972; Series I; 11
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Research Correspondence, is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - Adams, Stephen, 1964 Jul (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Antiquarian Society, 1964 Jan-Mar (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - British Museum, 1964 Mar-Apr (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brouwer, G. J., 1962 Aug 28 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clifford, James L., 1962-1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Haig, Robert, 1962 May-Jun (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hodgson, S., 1964 Jun-Aug (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Köster, Patricia, 1972 Jan-Mar (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - McEwen, Gilbert D., 1962 May-Jun (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library, 1964 May (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - University of Glasgow. Library, 1964 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Research Copies, n.d.; Series II; 16
  Series II, Research Copies, is arranged into two subseries: Primary Sources and Secondary Sources.
  - PRIMARY SOURCES
    - Ms Rawlinson D.71, Bodleian Library (undated)
      Bound photocopies
    - Ms Rawlinson D.72, Bodleian Library (ca. 1687-1718)
    - Ms Rawlinson D.72, Bodleian Library, copies of letters 59-63 (undated)
      Not included in the bound photocopy set of Ms Rawlinson D.72
    - Typescript, photostat, and manuscript copies of the will (1675 Mar 15) of Rev. John Dunton (1628-1676) (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Discarded binder included note, "Somerset House. Admons Book. Bunce, 1674. John Dunton."
    - Typescript copy of will (1711 Jun 20) of John Dunton (1659-1732) (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Will includes codicils dated 1720, 1729, and 1732.
    - Photostat copy of will (1711 Jun 20) of John Dunton (1659-1732)
    - John Dunton imprints (1680-1737) (Box 1, Folder 14-17)
    - John Dunton legal papers (1691-1708)
  - SECONDARY SOURCES
    - Theodore Merryman Hatfield, "The True Secret History of Mr. John Dunton", Ph.D. diss., Harvard University, 1926. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Papers removed from "The True Secret History of Mr. John Dunton" (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Dealer catalogs (1961, 1969), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Clippings removed from Sale Catalogues of Libraries of Eminent Persons, Vol. 5 (1972, 1974), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Volume cataloged separately
- Writings of Stephen Parks, 1968-69; Series III; 2
  Series III, Writings of Stephen Parks, is arranged chronologically.
  - Parks, Stephen. "John Dunton and The Works of The Learned." London: The Bibliographical Society, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Reprinted by The University Press, Oxford from the Transactions of The Bibliographical Society, The Library, March 1968. 2 copies
  - Parks, Stephen. "Booksellers' Trade Sales", 1969 Sep (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Reprinted from The Transactions of the Bibliographical Society, The Library, Vol. 24, no. 3, Sep 1969
- Oversize, 4.35; (3 boxes)
  - Ms Rawlinson D.72, Bodleian Library, copies of letters 59-63 (ca. 1687-1718) (in Series II) (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Photostat copy of will (1711 Jun 20) of John Dunton (1659-1732) (in Series II) (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Oversize John Dunton imprints (1681-1719) (in Series II) (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - John Dunton legal papers (1691-1708) (in Series II) (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Ms Rawlinson D.71, Bodleian Library (undated) (in Series II) (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Ms Rawlinson D.72, Bodleian Library (ca. 1687-1718) (in Series II) (Box 4, Folder 29)